Guide to the Abigail Belden Whelpley Papers 1807-1921, undated MS 3067
New-York Historical Society
Abigail Belden Whelpley papers
1807-1921, undated
New-York Historical Society
Whelpley, Abigail Belden, 1817-1880
MS 3067
.42 Linear Feet in one document box.
The collection primarily consists of manuscripts written by the Protestant author Abigail Belden Whelpley in the mid-1800s, including prose and poetry pieces most prominently on Christian thought and scripture, contemporary social issues, and the godliness of the natural world. Whelpley's writings also include commentary on the Civil War, the Temperance Society, and international affairs. Additionally, the papers contain correspondence and ephemera, including documents that concern Whelpley's father and son.
Arrangement
The collection largely retains its original order as received at purchase by N-YHS, contained in one document box. The folders are arranged with book chapters first, followed by essays, articles, short stories, and then poetry, with miscellaneous fragments and drafts completing the section on Whelpley's writings. The collection ends with correspondence and ephemera, which are organized chronologically within their folders when applicable. Folder labels are Whelpley's given document titles unless in brackets, in which case there was no title for the given documents and the folder label was devised by the processing archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Abigail Belden Whelpley was born in Hartford, Connecticut on 19 June 1817, to parents Rev. William Belden and Abigail Frances Hatch. Whelpley lived in New York City with her parents for most of her life, though she later moved to New Jersey and then Massachusetts to live with her brother and nephew. In 1841 she married Rev. Samuel Waldo Whelpley, who came from a family of clergymen similar to hers, and gave birth to her first and only son, Henry Belden Whelpley, in 1842. Though she spent some time working as a housekeeper, Abigail Belden Whelpley spent most of her time writing and contributing to various periodicals, including The Christian Family Annual, The Family Circle and Parlor Annual, and Youth's Parlor Annual. She died in 1880, and is buried in Brooklyn's Green-Wood Cemetery.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, March 2017.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily consists of manuscripts written by the Protestant author Abigail Belden Whelpley in the mid-1800s. The manuscripts include book chapters, articles, essays, and poems on a variety of topics, most prominently Christian thought and scripture, contemporary social issues, and the godliness of the natural world. Whelpley's writings also include commentary on the Civil War, the Temperance Society, and international affairs. Additionally, the papers contain correspondence, primarily between Abigail's son, Henry Belden Whelpley, and his cousin, William Belden, who was involved in the stock market crash of 1869, and ephemera, including documents from the early 1800s.
Christianity -- United States.; Epic poetry.; Poetry.; Protestantism.; Protestants -- United States.; Temperance -- New York (State) -- New York .; Women authors, American -- 19th century; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Articles; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Essays; Indentures.; Manuscripts (document genre); Periodicals; Belden, William, -1918; Whelpley, Abigail Belden, 1817-1880; Whelpley, Henry Belden, 1842-; Belden (Family: approximately 1807-1921)
- [Untitled Book], Vol. VI, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains draft of Chapters 23-26 of book of moral allegories and spiritual teachings written by Whelpley, labeled "Vol. VI" by the author. Chapter titles are "The Search," "Repentance," "The Sabbath," and "The Theatre."
- [Untitled Book], Vol. VII, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Contains Chapters 27-32 of book of moral allegories and spiritual teachings written by Whelpley, labeled "Vol. VII" by the author. Chapter titles are "Ruling Powers. King Puff," "King Humbug," "King Alcohol," "King Money," "King Fashion. Bishops," and "King Fashion Continued. Beards."
- "A few hints to young ladies upon mental cultivation in connexion with some branches of scientific and artistic study", Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Essay on the benefits of experiential, lifelong, and extensive education for young women.
- "Mr. Charles Dickens (Boz)", [1840s?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  A biting critique of Dickens and his work.
- [Essay on Scripture and Contemporary Politics], 1861 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Essay discussing the relationship between Christian spirituality and the social/labor revolutions of the mid to late 1800s. Includes thoughts on the Paris Commune, Karl Marx, and other contemporary figures and movements.
- "A little learning is a dangerous thing", Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Essay on remembering human ignorance in the face of holy omnipotence in order to inspire humility.
- "Some thoughts in connexion with the capabilities of the African race", Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Very short assessment of the achievements of the people of the African continent.
- "An Address delivered to the Female Benevolent Society, Waterville, Oneida County, N.Y.", 1842 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Speech on Christian scripture.
- [Pro-Temperance Society Essay], Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "The Christian Church divided into diverse sects a beautiful and useful arrangement", Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Music", Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Two copies of essay on the godliness of music and Creation.
- "Parental Duty", Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Labeled "original" by the author.
- "Have the Courts of the United States a right to determine that the Laws of the Union are unconstitutional?", Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Essay against judicial review.
- [Essay on Popular Literature], Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Meditations on God and the Scriptures", Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Popery Inconsistent with the Safety of A Free People", Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Sabbath", Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Essay on the sanctity of the Sabbath and in support of "Blue Laws" that prohibit certain forms of work on Sundays.
- "Our Emotional Nature", Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Essay on the holiness of the emotions with which God has endowed humankind, especially love.
- "Letter of a Mother to her son just entering upon the active duties of life", Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Advice for active citizenship and maintaining a strong moral character.
- "Guilt loves company", Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Short parable signed, "an observer," and labeled by the author, "For the Religious Inquirer."
- "The way to do good", Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Two copies of a parable about a young girl asking a matronly figure moral questions.
- "The length of the War not without some advantages", circa 1865 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Essay on the benefits of the Civil War lasting four years.
- "Bell, Book And Candle", Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Poem exploring a variety of themes, including the diversity of Christian beliefs.
- [Poem on General Pegram's Death], circa 1844? (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Poem about General James West Pegram's death in the 1844 Lucy Walker steamboat explosion.
- [Poem on Losing a Loved One], 1838 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- [Epic Poem About Darius Mede], Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Rhyming allegorical poem with scriptural and classical references.
- "David A Scripture Poem", Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Two copies of epic poem on King David, with many references to 1 Samuel and 2 Samuel from the Old Testament of the Bible and a dedication to God.
- [Writings on Native Americans in Connecticut], circa 1860 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Research on the history and contemporary state of the Native American population in Kent, Connecticut. Includes research on the descendants of the Pequot and Schaghticoke tribes.
- [Misc. Fragments and Drafts] (Folder 1 of 3), 1863, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Includes poetry and prose fragments on Christian scripture, nature, and personal anecdotes. Also contains a pro-Union piece on the victory at Gettysburg, written on 4 July 1863, and a peculiar piece on a free menagerie, perhaps an early zoo.
- [Misc. Fragments and Drafts] (2 folders of 3), 1859, 1864, undated (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  Includes poetry and prose fragments on Christian scripture, nature, classic literature, and personal anecdotes.
- [Correspondence] (Folder 1 of 2), 1917-1921 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Correspondence to Abigail Whelpley's son, Henry Belden Whelpley, from his cousin, William Belden, who was involved in the "Black Friday" stock market crash that resulted from James Fisk, Jay Gould, and Belden's attempt to corner the gold market in 1869 (though this is not a subject of the correspondence). Contains the last letters Belden wrote before his death, and letters from his wife, Anna, to settle Belden's affairs after the fact.
- [Correspondence] (Folder 2 of 2), 1871-1921 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Includes various miscellaneous pieces of correspondence and personal financial documents, including a letter to Henry Belden Whelpley from Fanny Harrod (James Fisk's wife's lover), an invitation to Henry Belden Whelpley's wedding, a letter to Henry Belden Whelpley from the former Attorney General of New Jersey, Robert Gilchrist, Jr., and other communications to and from various members of the Belden family.
- [Ephemera and Print Matter], 1846-1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Includes illustrations of holy relics, painted flowers, a flower-engraved book cover, and copies of Protestant periodicals such as two copies of the 1846 edition of the North American Protestant or Anti-Jesuit Magazine, three copies of The Family Circle and Parlor Annual from 1845-1847, with Abigail Belden Whelpley's published work inside, and the cover of an 1852 edition of The Ladies Wreath: A Magazine.
- [Legal Documents] (Folder 1 of 2), 1807, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  1807 certificate of William Belden's status as a freeman of Danbury, having taken the freeman's oath, and a contract for William Belden's 1826 land purchase for land in Witton, Fairfield County, Connecticut.
- [Legal Documents] (Folder 2 of 2), 1824 (Box Oversize Small)
  William Belden's oversized warranty deed / indenture for property in the Seventh Ward of New York City.